Before we get into the code and start correcting for
コードの説明に移って ひずみの補正を始める前に
distortion, let's get some intuition as to how this distortion occurs.
このひずみがどのようにして起こるかを 理解しておきましょう
Here's a simple model of a camera called the pinhole camera model.
これはカメラのシンプルなモデルで ピンホールカメラモデルといいます
When the camera forms an image,
カメラは画像を作るとき
it's looking at the world similar to how our eyes do.
私たちの目の動きと同じように 実世界を見ています
By focusing the light that's reflected off of objects in the world.
光を集中させることにより 光が 実世界の物体で反射します
In this case through a small pinhole, the camera focuses the light that's
この場合 小さなピンホールを通して カメラは光を集中させ これが
reflected off of a 3D traffic sign, and forms a 2D image
3D の交通標識で反射して 2D 画像の形成が
at the back of the camera or a sensor or some film would be placed.
カメラの奥で行われます センサーまたはフィルムが付いていることもあります
In fact the image it forms here will be upside down, and
実際には ここで形成される画像は 上下反転して逆になります
reversed because rays of light that enter from the top of an object
なぜなら光線は 物体の上部から入ってきて
will continue on that angled path through the pinhole and
その角度の進路のままピンホールを通過し
end up at the bottom of the formed image.
形成される画像の下部まで 続くからです
Similarly, light that reflects off the right side of an object
同様に 物体の右側で 反射する光は
will travel to the left of the formed image.
形成される画像の左側に 伝わります
In math this transformation from 3D object points, P of X, Y, and Z.
数学ではこの変換 つまり 3D オブジェクトポイント P (X, Y, Z) から
To 2D image points, P of just X, and
2D イメージポイント p (x, y) への変換は
Y is done by a transformative matrix called the camera matrix.
カメラ行列という 変換行列によって行います
Which I'll call C for camera and
これを カメラを表す C と呼ぶことにします
we'll need this to calibrate the camera later on.
後ほどカメラのキャリブレーションで 必要になります
However, real cameras don't use tiny pinholes like this,
ただ 実際のカメラは このような小さなピンホールを使いません
they use lenses to focus multiple light rays at a time.
レンズを使用して 複数の光線を一度に集中させます
Which allows them to quickly form images.
そうすることで すばやく画像を形成できます
But lenses can introduce distortion too.
でもレンズはひずみも起こすことがあります
Light rays often bend a little too much or
光線の屈折が少し大きすぎたり 小さすぎることが
too little at the edges of a curved lens of a camera, and this creates the effect
湾曲したカメラレンズの端ではよく起こります これによって生じる影響は
we looked at earlier that distorts the edges of images.
先ほど説明した 画像の端のひずみです
So that lines or objects appear, more or less, curved than they actually are.
そのため 線や物体は実際よりも 多少湾曲して見えます
This is called radial distortion, and it's the most common type of distortion.
これは放射状ひずみと呼ばれ 最も一般的な種類のひずみです
Another type, is tangential distortion, if the camera's lens is not aligned
もう 1 つのタイプは 接線ひずみです カメラのレンズの配置が
perfectly parallel to the imaging plane where the camera film or
カメラのフィルムやセンサーがある画像面に 完全に平行になっていない場合
sensor is, this makes an image look tilted.
これによって 画像が傾いて見えます
So that some objects appear further away or closer than they actually are.
そのため 一部の物体は実際よりも 遠くまたは近くに見えます
And this is tangential distortion.
これが接線ひずみです
There are even example of lenses that purposefully distort images like fisheye
レンズの中には意図的に画像のひずみを 起こす例さえあって たとえば魚眼レンズや
or wide angle lenses which keep radial distortion for stylistic effect.
広角レンズはスタイル効果のために 放射状ひずみの状態を保ちます
But for our purposes we are using this images
でも 私たちの目的では この画像を使用して
to position ourself driving car and eventually steer it the right direction.
自動運転車を位置調整し 最終的には正しい方向に進ませます
So we need undistorted images that accurately reflect
そこで必要になるのが 画像のひずみを除去して
our real world surroundings.
正確に実世界の環境を映すことです
Luckily, this distortion can generally be captured by five numbers called
幸い このひずみは一般に 5 つの数で取得できます
distortion coefficients, whose values reflect the amount of radial and
この数をひずみ係数といい 各値が示すのは 放射状ひずみと
tangential distortion in an image.
接線ひずみの画像内の量です
In severely distorted cases, sometimes even more than
ひずみの程度が大きいと 場合によっては
five coefficients are required to capture the amount of distortion.
ひずみの量を取得するために 5 つを上回る係数さえ必要になります
If we know these coefficients,
これらの係数がわかれば
we can use them to calibrate our camera and undistort our images.
係数を使ってカメラのキャリブレーションと 画像のひずみ除去ができます
And the mathematical details of correcting for
ひずみの補正に関する 数学的な詳細は
distortion are in the notes below.
下の注記にあります
Next we'll see how to get these coefficients and calibrate a camera.
次に これらの係数を取得して カメラのキャリブレーションを行う方法を見ていきます